Finding Aid for Marian McCracken papers, 1968-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marian McCracken papers 1968-1999
McCracken, Marian, 1920-
1 linear foot.
9643 Aa 2
Teacher, feminist, president of the Michigan Conference of the National Organization for Women and other women's rights and feminist organizations. Biographical materials, files detailing N.O.W. activities and her involvement in the People's Campaign for Choice, a group established in 1987-1988 to block passage of a bill banning Medicaid payments for abortion.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was acquired in several accessions from Marian McCracken (Donor No. 8485 ) beginning in 1996.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Marian McCracken has been active in the Michigan feminist movement since the 1950s and is particularly noted for her leadership role in the Michigan Conference of the National Organization for Women (NOW). McCracken graduated in 1942 from Wayne State University with a bachelor's degree in fine arts and received her master's degree from that university in 1974. Her crusade for women's rights began in earnest in 1957 when she entered the workforce after her husband was diagnosed with multiple sclerosis. After earning her teaching certificate, McCracken taught for the Farmington Public Schools until her retirement in 1982.
At the beginning of her 23-year teaching career, McCracken noticed disparities in administrative opportunities for men and women in the educational system. She was also disturbed that gender stereotyping created an inequity in sports programs for girls and boys and negatively affected students' attitudes. These problems and others encouraged McCracken to become involved in the women's rights movement. She held offices in the National Education Association at the local, state, and national level, was elected president of the Michigan Education Association's Women's Caucus, and was a member of the American Association of University Women (AAUW).
Since her retirement from teaching, McCracken has devoted much of her energy to feminist activism and advocacy. She has participated in the Democratic Party, Gray Panthers, People's Campaign for Choice, Farmington chapter of the Older Women's League, Michigan Women's Studies Association, and Michigan Women's Assembly. She served three terms as president of the Michigan Conference of NOW (1986-1989) and was elected to the NOW national board in 1988. Largely through her association with NOW, the nation's largest feminist rights organization, McCracken has fought for Medicaid funding for abortion, increased participation of women in politics, the ERA amendment, pay equity, and childcare. Her dedication to teaching and to Michigan feminism have earned her numerous awards, including the Detroit NOW "Feminist of the Year Award" (1983), a special tribute from Governor James Blanchard and the Michigan House of Representatives (1986), the AAUW's "Women's Community Enrichment Award" (1987), and induction into the Farmington Teacher Hall of Fame (1989).
The papers of Marian McCracken document McCracken's participation in the feminist movement in Michigan from 1968 to 1996, with particular attention to her involvement with the National Organization for Women, 1985-1992. The collection is organized into a single topical series, arranged alphabetically. Files relating to NOW comprise the majority of the collection. The State Coordinating Council file of the Michigan section of these files provides succinct information about Michigan NOW's organizational structure. The Issues file documents NOW's response to the 1987 nomination of Judge Robert Bork to the Supreme Court, the 1987 papal visit to Detroit, and NOW's 1988 clashes with Domino's Pizza.
Other important files include the Biographical folder, which contain articles summarizing McCracken's achievements; Michigan feminist organizations and issues, which provides insights into Michigan's feminist movement apart from NOW; and records relating to People's Campaign for Choice, a group organized in 1987-1988 to block passage of a bill banning Medicaid payments for abortion. The collection as a whole documents not only the life of an important Michigan feminist but also the life of the Michigan feminist movement.
Subjects:
McCracken, Marian, 1920-; Feminists--Michigan.; National Organization for Women. Michigan Conference.; Peoples Campaign for Choice.
- Topical file
  - Biographical materials, 1976-1996 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Democratic Party Women's Caucus, 1982-1995 (Box 1)
  - Michigan feminist organizations (miscellaneous), 1986-1992 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW)
    - Re: Detroit all-male school, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Conference
      - Correspondence, 3 folders
        - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
        - 1987 (Box 1)
        - 1988 (Box 1)
      - Issues, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
      - Local chapters (organized alphabetically), 1988 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (including by-laws), 1986-1995 (Box 1)
      - News clippings and releases, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
      - Newsletter ("Hotline"), 1986-1999 (Box 1)
      - Oakland County chapter, newsletter, 1992-1996 (Box 1)
      - State conference, 1983-1989 (Box 1)
      - State Coordinating Council, 1985-1992 (Box 1)
    - National Board, Great Lakes Region, 1988-1992 (Box 1)
    - National Policy Manual, 1985-1987 (?) (Box 1)
  - People's Campaign for Choice, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
  - Political miscellanea, 1982-1992 (Box 1)
  - Teaching career and interests, ca. 1968-1995 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - 1998 accession, 1 binder and 1 folder (Box 1)
  - 2001 accession, 2 folders (Box 1)